[Music]
let's talk
money welcome back you're with us on
let's talk money and this week it's all
about travel how to plan better plan
smarter and how to ensure that you have
the right kind of travel insurance as
you're rushing out towards the airport
Priya deshmuk is with us in the studios
she's from icsi Lombard and she's
helping us understand all the
nitty-gritties of a travel policy
typically I admit this is the last thing
people sort of look into which is why
we're here to ask the questions prya so
what all does a travel policy cover I
should know beforehand right rather than
Landing up in a in a problem outside and
then figuring out okay does my policy
absolutely have this or not absolutely
one of the surveys by Global Travel U
Trends report 50% of people travel you
know book their tickets 14 days in
advance and almost similar numbers uh
buy insurance in the last two days of
the travel that's planned for so it's
very much of a last minute kind of a uh
you know Affair but it's very critical
for people to understand that the
country that they're visiting what is
the kind of healthare system how are
things and in order to really avoid the
last minute you know hassle or any issue
that is caused because of any medical
emergency or non-medical uh you know
situations of loss of baggage or mugging
or any kind of other mishaps it's
important to really buy insurance and
know what what all your insurance plans
really covers so does the insurance plan
cover something like mugging as well yes
yes yes I mean uh almost um you know 30%
of Indians that take trips uh there is a
situation where uh they have had uh
issue with mugging any fraudulent
payment other challenges I mean those
are common issues that Travelers really
experience um there are um you know
instances where people get tricked so
all of these elements are covered as
part of uh non-medical coverage in the
insurance tra travel insurance plan so
you have the basic critical you know
vanilla offering of medical insurance
any kind of emergency any
hospitalization for that matter any kind
of personal accident but at the same
time you have loss of baggage loss of
passport you know all those kind of
issues also covered as part of the
offering so are these plans fairly
standardized across the industry or do
you have to be very careful and go
through all the conditions because maybe
IC Lombard is offering maybe someone
else is is not uh so the reason I'm
asking is that you know we don't
typically pay so much attention to what
all is covered see in the zest of travel
and most of most of the travel is either
for leisure or study or maybe work
related travel people tend to really uh
miss out and pay as much attention that
one would uh need for a travel insurance
plan and the travel insurance plan would
uh choice would essentially depend on
the destination as I said uh what kind
of uh uh long stay or a short stay what
is the family combination that is
traveling and and what is the
infrastructure in the city uh what are
the local uh you know uh situations or
scenarios that are going to impact
either health or uh you know non-health
kind of situations that the traveler May
face and hence it's extremely important
to go through the details of what your
policy covers what are the critical U
exclusion lists and also be familiarized
as to if at all there is a claim to be
made what are the processes to really go
through uh you know if one has to go
through that you know scenario or a
situation no absolutely so that which is
why I was asking that all the things
that you you kind of listed out which is
the medical emergency which is a
non-medical emergency which could be
loss of baggage which could be things
like you know mugging or theft or you
know loss of documents do most insurers
in the average travel insurance policy
do do most insurers cover this so uh
there's something called as basic cover
and uh now New Age products cover
multiple other features so there is a
bare minimum Medical emergency and loss
of baggage kind of feature okay uh
however uh there are a lot of novelty
kind of features that have been added by
New Age insurance companies like
ourselves so you have Adventure Sport
you have Visa Service uh so you apply
for a Visa your Visa gets rejected so
your insurance covers the entire
processing fee uh so that's something
new uh you know adventure sports was
always excluded but uh now it's all
about experiential uh you know traveling
and it's important for you to really
have that assurance and that uh you know
security so uh there are plants which
are very very customizable they can be
personalized depending on the need for
your travel the stay uh the uh number of
days that you're staying in a particular
country uh the requirement that's there
so the newer plants the new age plants
do have customization options available
and it would have impact on uh your
coverages as well as the cost of travel
insurance premium that you would so got
that for now to go back to the example
that you gave earlier about a
50-year-old traveling to any
International destination right uh you
said the cover there would be around
10,700 but that's for a 180 days of
foreign stay correct correct that's
right I mean that's a long stay uh you
could have programs where you're going
for for a Leisure
trip two weeks or all uh so you have a
different kind of uh premium which is
much much uh uh you know kind of uh uh
smaller compared to what I mentioned and
depending on the country that you're
going it would again differ and uh the
premiums are really really very economic
even even for something like Adventure
Sports and all the funky there's a
little bit of layer of U you know risk
out there and you load up as a insurer
you would load up the premium but uh
still it would be much much cheaper
ballpark estimates say a 2 three week
trip uh the basic cover which includes
your you know medical emergency loss of
baggage and throw in that Adventure
cover so how much would it cost 6,000 to
7,000 range is the premium that you
would have for a 2 we uh you know uh
travel and some of these add-ons that
are uh you know kind of I mentioned just
now would be the ballbar number okay
Priya so that's really helpful finally
now Summit all up for us what are the
things that we should check read ask
before buying travel insurance um you
know as we discussed throughout um you
know travel insurance is one of the most
important and core um uh you know
requirement one when somebody is
traveling either for leisure or business
or any kind of tour and the last thing
you want is to be stuck by any kind of a
situation and get caught in the middle
of a problem uh having said that um you
know in travel insurance is to give you
Assurance peace of mind uh one must
check uh what are the exclusions and
inclusions depending on the you know
what kind of coverage do you have what
country you're traveling if you're
traveling to a country like a um you
know us or Europe or any other country
having high amount of um you know
medical expenses when it comes to
medical emergencies you got to really
make sure that you have adequate some
insured uh check the start date and end
date uh of your travel insurance policy
depending on the travel dates that
you're traveling Al also the
geographical scope in terms of coverages
restrictions and exclusions and uh
familiarize yourself with the claim uh
process and depending on your
requirement and need you know uh certain
add-on New Age covers that are there
whether it is sports and Adventure car
rentals you know we've seen almost 20%
of people who travel abroad now prefer
to have you know rental cars
uh so to cover that bit of any kind of
damage or any mishap you have insurance
cover addon so such kind of addon covers
align to your itenary on uh your leisure
and the trip that you're planning you
have to really make sure that all of
that is kind of concerted and kind of
aligned with your plan Priya that's a
really important point and before we go
we must ask you in the event of a mishap
something gets lost you lose your phone
you lose your documents God forbid a
medical emergency what's the process
what do you do you call back to India
how how does the claim happen explain
the process so for in case of a u you
know non-medical emergency like a flight
gets cancelled or there is a baggage
loss so we have a auto tracking
mechanism and autoc claim reimbursement
or uh you know kind of payoff to the
consumer so it's completely hassle-free
the last last thing we want our
Travelers or you know insured members to
really worry about how do you claim in
case of travel being cancelled because
of trip cancellation which is very well
uh you know available as an information
and we have integration to really get
that info transmitted uh similarly
talking about uh uh you know medical
emergency we have our partners across
the globe uh you know there are plant
worldwide cover there are certain
geographical uh specific uh you know
plants that you uh buy we have uh a
clearly mentioned U you know phone line
number our
application yeah we have an application
where in the consumer can go in and uh
just dial that uh you know uh uh
toll-free number connect with a partner
and the whole end to endend handholding
of the whole process will be taken care
by a partner so this is a 24x7 um you
know facility that is available in case
of emergency any kind of uh you know
kind of uh uh transmission from or
rather uh any kind of Transit that has
to be arranged from one location to
another if there is an accident uh a
person has to be moved from that
particular location of an accident to
the nearest facility all of that
ambulance services and any kind of uh
support uh to offer all of that is being
managed by our and how quick is this
emergency response and uh in case of
emergency it would uh range anywhere
between 30 minutes to 2 hours depending
on the criticality of the situation so
we have Partnerships across the globe uh
whether it is Hospital partnership or
you know any other network partnership
those are in place for us to support our
customers very very reassuring to hear
but hopefully we we don't you know need
those uh Services when we travel but
always good to be secured know that
you're covered in case of any
eventuality PR very very helpful
conversation thank you very much it was
a pleasure thank you very much wish you
a fabulous 2025 more travel more joy and
more secure trips ahead thank you all
right with that it's a wrap on this
week's edition of let's talk money thank
you for watching we'll see you again
with the Final Countdown the final
episode of 2024 coming up next week
[Music]
let's talk money